Have you ever heard of a protein called
betain?
No? Well, that's because it's a popular
one in cell biology and human
physiology, but it's not a common one in
the clinical world. But research
strongly indicates that it plays a
powerful role in keeping inflammation
throughout your body in check. The same
inflammation linked to diabetes,
obesity, cardiovascular disease, cancer,
and more. And the kicker, your nutrition
can severely reduce its levels in your
body, leading to greater inflammation
and greater disease risk. So, let's
discuss what beta does, why it's
important, although you've probably
never heard of it, and what to do to
keep it elevated in your body. This
actually starts in your body fat,
specifically a type of body fat called
visceral fat. Visceral fat wraps around
and in your organs, and it's been
heavily linked to inflammation, but
exactly how it contributes to bodily
inflammation has been a point of heavy
research considering its links to health
harm. We'll touch on that later again.
So in this study, the researchers
uncovered how visceral fat controls your
immune cells and they even showed how to
control your visceral fat to stop
causing a pro-inflammatory state through
its immune control. What the researchers
did is take visceral fat samples and
separate out the cells found inside the
visceral fat. They can do that using a
research technique called fax or
fluorescent activated cell sorting.
Essentially, they identify cells by
specific features on the cell surface.
Like you recognize people that you know
through looking at features on their
face. We can see that data here. I
realize this looks like a lot, but it's
actually pretty simple. Just unfocus
your eyes and pay attention to where the
color is located in each square. On the
far left, they're separating out
specific sections of the visceral fat.
And as they move to the right, they're
using finer and finer tooth comb to
separate out only immune cells, removing
fat cells and other cells called stromal
cells until we end up at the end. The
cells that have a ZDC
GFP on the bottom axis there. If the
cells have high levels of ZDC, they are
a particular type of immune cell called
a dendritic cell. And if they have less
on the left there, they have a different
immune cell that isn't a dendritic cell
called a monocy. The takeaway here is
that your fat contains immune cells of
which a subpopul are dendritic cells.
Okay. Well, why does that matter? Well,
we're talking about inflammation, which
is heavily reliant on these subpopuls of
cells. These dendritic cells are what's
known as antigen presenting cells,
meaning that they literally present or
activate the rest of the immune cells to
be more pro-inflammatory. They'll start
releasing molecules that lead to a more
aggressive immune system called
cytoines, and they'll physically
activate more specialized immune cells,
but we clearly don't want that if
there's no infection or no need for the
immune system to be active. So keep that
in mind. unnecessary inflammation is bad
and dendritic cells play a key role in
inducing inflammation. Okay. So the
researchers have this population of
dendritic cells and even within the
dendritic cells there is a subpopul in
this case CDC1 and CDC2 dendritic cells.
Here we're looking at key proteins
within both subpopuls of dendritic
cells. Notice the designations up top.
Then on the right we have a few
different proteins. You might recognize
one of them. That's right, betaaten.
Since we're measuring protein levels,
just think of the darker and larger the
splotch, the more protein is there.
Clearly the CDC1 dendritic cells have
far more betain because if you compare
the two, there's a darker splotch. Okay,
but we now have our introduction to
betain. But how does that translate to
inflammation? Well, there's a common
marker of inflammation. Remember when I
mentioned that immune cells like
dendritic cells release different
pro-inflammatory factors called
cytoines? Well, a common one is called
interlucan 6 or IL6. You can actually
get this test done for yourself at least
on a whole body level. So the more IL6
generally that's an indication of more
inflammation, a bad thing in this
context. Okay. So here we have IL6
levels. We don't need to go over all
this. Don't worry. The researchers are
using a pro-inflammatory stimulator
there, GLA. So sometimes you see a plus,
you know, they added the inflammation
stimulator. If the bars go up, that
means there's more IL6, so greater
inflammation signaling. And we see
that's true for both dendritic cell
subtypes in visceral fat here and here.
However, the researchers were interested
in finding out what happens when you
stimulate betain.
So they added beta katin activator
called SB216763
which was the runner up for the name for
terminator but they ended up going with
T800 because uh this molecule had dibs.
So when SB is also added to the cells
you can clearly see there's a huge
decrease in IL6. And notice how it's
only really dramatically effective in
the CDC1 dendritic cells. That makes
sense considering we know it has more
betaetin in it. So the takeaway here is
that certain dendritic cells found in
visceral fat have higher levels of this
protein called betaine and activating
this protein dramatically reduces
inflammatory profile of these cells at
least by this measure. But I'll go ahead
and tell you that the researchers
confirm these results across other
measures as well. All right, we see the
connection between beta in our immune
cells and inflammation. But I did say
visceral fat controls these immune
cells, but we haven't proven exactly
how. The researchers took similar
samples of visceral fat and measured
proteins known to activate betaine
called the Wint pathway. Specifically,
Wint 10 is the name of the protein. Now,
I won't bore you with the data, but they
show that there's a big increase in Wint
release by the visceral fat tissue. And
when they applied Wint to the dendritic
cells, look, it's the same conditions
measuring IL6 and we're still applying
this GLA inflammatory molecule and SB
activator for the betain. And they've
also added this Went 10 protein. And you
can clearly see there's a huge reduction
in IL6 pro-inflammation signaling. And
beyond that, it's equivalent to the
betaine specific activator, offering
greater credence to the idea that
betaetin is activated by wind. And this
is how visceral fat reduces
inflammation.
Wait a minute, guy. Visceral fat reduces
That's not what you were telling me
earlier. Well, that's true. But just
because we see Wint does reduce
inflammatory profile doesn't mean that
visceral fat is continuously releasing
Wint and that's actually where your
nutrition plays a role because it can
increase or reduce W from your fat
tissue thereby indirectly affecting
betaine. So before we get to that,
there's a lot that I skipped over on the
beta catin like its other unique effects
in our immune system, but there's also
another powerful protein that has
similar benefits, but works differently
and is also heavily affected by
different habits along with more
targeted ways of improving the
anti-inflammatory effects of dendritic
cells and a lot more. But since I can't
cover it here, I'm covering it in the
extended version of this video that
you're watching, which is included with
the Physionic Insiders, my premium
research platform. And wouldn't you
believe it, you get so much other stuff
if you join, like the stuff on the
screen right now, a podcast, live
sessions with me, and more. Link is in
the description if you're interested.
So, why would visceral fat reduce went
release, thereby reducing betaine and
encourage a pro-inflammatory state?
Well, the researchers have been testing
all this in mice and simply changed
their diet and then measured a whole
host of different WIN proteins as seen
here. That line across them is the
normal W levels. And if they fall below
that line, the diet leads to significant
reductions in wind. Now, while some look
like they reduce, we only see a
statistically significant effect for the
very same WIN protein that we looked at
earlier, WIN 10. Further, if we look at
the same betaine protein levels on the
normal diet called CIA or this other
diet WD, can you guess what that stands
for? And we compare the protein levels
in the same CDC1 dendritic cells, we see
a reduction in betaine. So the takeaway
here being that our diet can reduce
release from visceral fat tissue and our
diet can reduce the levels of this
anti-inflammatory protein betain. So
what is WD and does this apply to humans
considering the mechanism nature of this
study and what can be done to encourage
more W signaling and greater beta
levels. WD for those that didn't figure
it out stands for western diet or more
specifically a diet rich in sugar
saturated fats and calories. So by these
data a poor diet classified as a western
diet here increases the odds of a
pro-inflammatory state by our visceral
fat. Now, while I'd love to tell you
there's strong research indicating a
link between beta and went and chronic
disease, I can't do that. There's a few
studies that look at beta in humans, but
they are sparse and tend not to look at
the outcomes that we're interested in.
In addition, some show increases, some
show decreases again because there's a
lot of differences between studies. So
no, there's currently little good
research linking betain and inflammation
from visceral fat. However, there are
plenty of studies that show a strong
link between visceral fat and
inflammation in humans. So while we
can't confirm the finer details, the
overall point seems pretty strong.
Visceral fat can contribute to a
pro-inflammatory immune profile, which
in turn is linked to worse health. So,
how do we encourage betaetinine and
reduce this pro-inflammatory state? A
quick mention, I could have easily made
some pretty incredibly bad jokes about
betaine because, okay, listen to this
real quick. Betaine is activated by Wint
when Wint binds to a receptor called
Frizled. Yes, frizled. Like uh the magic
school bus, Miss Frizzle. But it gets
better because Frizled activates a
protein called
disheveled. I find those names
hilarious. I mean, frizled and
disheveled are saving you from
inflammation by protecting betaanine.
Sounds like some parents taking care of
their kids in the morning pre- coffee on
a Monday, frizzled and disheveled. Too
funny. Anyway, how should we summarize
this? And what are some easy actionable
takeaways? Well, we learned that
visceral fat tissue can change the
amount of wind protein it releases which
binds specific immune cells called
dendritic cells. These dendritic cells
once bound by wind have more active
betain which reduces the amount of
pro-inflammatory molecules like
interlucan 6 from being produced among
other inflammatory benefits. A typical
western diet reduces went release by
visceral fat leading to reduced betain
and increasing inflammation which tracks
with greater disease risk. So a few
things that you can focus on to maintain
elevated betain are one eat more
satiating foods whole foods. It'll make
a big difference on if you overconume or
not. Two in the same vein cut the
ultrarocessed foods. They do the exact
opposite. Number three, reduce the
number of times that you eat out per
week. Most foods made in restaurants are
highly calorically dense. Four, simply
cut back or eliminate calorie richch
drinks like sugary drinks. Soda is a
perfect example. All those contribute to
a western diet and the negative effects
that we just went over. But there are
also ways of reducing visceral fat
dramatically as well as nuances related
to visceral fat that I cover right here.
I'll speak with you over there. Thanks
for tuning in.